<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>draft on Objective Funk</title>
    <link>http://nsaphra.github.io/tags/draft/</link>
    <description>Recent content in draft on Objective Funk</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 18:11:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://nsaphra.github.io/tags/draft/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What Does a Coder Do If They Can&#39;t Type?</title>
      <link>http://nsaphra.github.io/post/hands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 18:11:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nsaphra.github.io/post/hands/</guid>
      <description>In August of 2015, my hands stopped working. I could still control them, but every movement accumulated more pain, so every motion came with a cost: getting dressed in the morning, sending a text, lifting a glass. In relating this story, I often mention that for months before I learned to work without my hands, I had nothing to do but go to a bar and order a shot of vodka with a straw in it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Graph Theory</title>
      <link>http://nsaphra.github.io/post/spectral-graph-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 18:11:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nsaphra.github.io/post/spectral-graph-theory/</guid>
      <description>My goal here is to explain some basic elements of spectral graph theory to myself. This post may also be useful to an audience with a similar background to mine, including rudimentary linear algebra and lay-computer-scientist exposure to graph theory.
Spectral graph theory is concerned with the analysis of a graph in terms of the eigenvectors, algebraic and geometric multiplicities, and other properties of matrix representations of the graph. These properties provide a way of efficiently extracting properties of the graph itself, such as communities and stability.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>